Welcome back, you are watching Bano, our
Finance Minister and I am with you. I had
told you that please let's move ahead with the show and now let's
talk about insurance, life
insurance and health insurance. Now
a question regarding this is very common and
we are often asked on the show as well,
what are the complications regarding claims settlement?
In what circumstances,
due to what actions, your life insurance or
your health insurance can be rejected. We will
talk about this in detail.
Naval Goyal, Founder and CEO of policyx.com has
joined me. Welcome to
our special presentation and we will
talk about both types of insurance.
First of all, let's start with life insurance,
where I think claim rejection can be
very heavy for you financially, that is
why it is very important.
As Naval, we have often discussed with you as well
and we tell people that the
biggest reason for claim rejection is
not providing correct information.
This issue is very common in life insurance
and because of this, we have seen that
people get life insurance worth crores of rupees and keep it.  If it gets
red then that
claim gets rejected so when we say
Naval that you should give your information correctly
what does it mean
Kavita so basically
if we think from the perspective of the insurance company then
they reject the claim only
when they feel that there has been some problem
activity in the policy or the policy
holder did
not give the correct disclosure while taking the policy due to which their
decision of giving insurance or not could have changed, then how does the
insurance company say that I will
not give you the policy at all, if you had given this
disclosure then definitely there could have been a
claim dictation in that situation, so
when we are filling the proposal form then we should
ensure that we fill everything accurately, filling
accurately does not mean that
you do not hide anything from your side, do not
say anything, do not lie, but for
example if you are not non-spoken
and you write it then
what happens from that  There is a
huge difference in the premium, so if the insurance
company says that you
lied at the time of proposing, then that becomes a ground for
rejecting the claim, so it is definitely the same
thing, if you have a genuine claim, there are
no issues, in 99% of the claims there was no problem even with the story, it has happened
only in cases
where either there was some problem activity or the
customer lied while proposing,
you are absolutely right Naval and that is why we
see that when people buy their life insurance and
especially insurance, they
look at the claim settlement ratio and they
also like the claim settlement ratio of the company,
they feel that the
claims here are settled well, so
how right would it be to look at the clean settlement ratio before buying life insurance,
Naval,
so this is a very important number, basically it
tells that if the insurance company has received
100 claims late, if their
clean settlement ratio is 99, then it means
that 100  Out of these, 99 claims have been
settled by the insurance company, one claim has been repeated
or is still pending, so
if it has been repeated then for what reason it has been done, a genuine reason has to be given
because IRDA is
a governing body, they have some rules and regulations
that you cannot reject any claim just like that,
so the insurance company has to
give an answer for every claim that due to this reason
they have rejected the claim and that reason should be
very sound, legally and legally sound, so
definitely if the customer is
buying insurance then definitely he should
not have any such check that the claim will be
rejected unless and until he himself is
doing a prudent activity or is
hiding something or he basically
delays the claim intimation, but
in Example Life, there is no such issue even if you
delay in applying the claim,
because many times what happens is that life
insurance  In UNO family members, they are
not even aware that such a policy existed. Late after the
UNO date, after two years, the
nominee finds out that the
policy was lying with them. Then they
can apply for UNO claim in the policy and
give the reason that they were not aware that the UNO date existed
and they got the policy somehow.
If it is found to be a genuine reason,
if the UNO date is genuine, then how are
claims settled? If an unfortunate incident happens
in someone's family, then first of all the
nominees should have information about what kind of
insurance policy has been made,
what has been insured for what all.
Once this information is available, then
what is the process after that for claiming it
and what other things do you have to bear.
So, we have seen a lot that people's
UNO family members are not even aware
that any policy is lying with them. So, we at least
want to tell our UNO customers
that there is definitely a repository type of information for whatever policy they are buying.  They can
either create an online excel sheet which they can
share with their family members. Now
suppose they have everything like policy number etc., then the
first thought is that if something untoward happens, then
their job is to intimate the insurance
company that such and such has happened and then the
insurance company's You Know Claim
System itself guides them as to
what to do. So if we
talk about term insurance, then definitely they just have to
prove that the death has occurred
and they had a policy and they basically do a
basic check. In most of the cases, nowadays the
claim is being approved very quickly within
10-15 days. In fact, many
insurance companies pay the money and the
insurance company does
not. Apart from this, there are other criteria
under which your life insurance claim can be rejected.
Not providing correct information. I
think you have explained that in detail, that
means basically it is something which can be
repudiated, there are some other reasons
which are not covered but for example,
suicide attack, suicide is only covered in some policies.  It is
not covered for 12 months and then it happens later, so
if death occurs due to suicide within
6 months of you purchasing the
policy, then how can that be represented?
Secondly, if someone commits an illegal act
or you commit a drink and
drive act, then any such thing which
we should not do generally, which
is illegal or drink and drive,
claims can be represented in such things,
but now they come to some orange where there are
two types of coverage, one is cashless
and many times people also get reimbursement
if they go to any out of cashless hospital and get
their treatment done,
but we are talking about the health insurance claim,
it is examined very closely by the
insurance company and their
special team of doctors, so
now tell me in such a situation, due to which a claim can be represented,
so number one is that if
that coverage is not there in the policy, then definitely the claim can be
rejected or there is some limit, but  For
example, there is a limit on late cataract that
you cannot spend more than Rs 60,000, so if you
spend Rs 1 lakh, you will get only Rs 60,000,
you will have to pay the claim of Rs 40,000 yourself. So, there are
limits in this type of policy, there are
some elements and some
exclusions from pre-existing diseases, but for
example, if you told at the time of taking the policy that
this is your disease, then the insurance company
says that we will not cover this disease for 4 years, then in that case the
claim is definitely
rejected. Third thing is that if your
mother has looked into everything, there is coverage,
everything is there, but you
delayed filing, you filed your reverse
hospitalization claim after 30
days, 45 days, 60 days, then
nowadays we are seeing that some insurance companies are directly
rejecting it saying that you have
delayed a lot in filing the claim and
some companies are also processing it, so
this  We have seen a recent phenomenon in
which delay in filing of investment
claims is also becoming a major reason for
claim repudiation. If it is a cashless
treatment, then definitely you
go to the hospital and intimacy and they
approve it. And if it is a reimbursement, then
we suggest that you register the claim within 24 to
48 hours at the listed insurance company.
This does not mean that
you are providing documents, but at least if you
call and say that I have come for this treatment
and I am getting treatment in this hospital, then the
chances of your claim getting rejected are
reduced considerably, unless there are any exclusions
or any particular elements which are
not already covered in your policy.
In such a situation also, I think documents are very
important, Naval. And when you have
given the reimbursement and when you leave the hospital,
what kind of documents should you insist on
which the company asks for?  And in the
absence of which your claim can also be rejected.
So basically, we suggest
that maximum times you should remember the name of the U N O
cashless hospital near you
so that it goes into it, because there is
so much documentation at the
time of return that you have to
read the unnecessary documentation in the hair style,
but still, if you do
not get the opportunity to go into U N O cashless, then
for reimbursement, you definitely have to deposit all the
medical bills starting from the discharge slip
and plus the doctor's diagnosis due to which
you had to go to the hospital,
all those documents have to be submitted
to the nearest branch of the U N O insurance company
or you have to submit them
because through that, basically the insurance
company has more
U N O interest relief in two things
or not, you had any such problem, what was the
cost and the detailing of your cost, how much
cost was incurred in which thing,
because in many policies there
is a limit for the last, but for example, there is a limit for room rent  If
you have taken a room for ₹5000 or ₹7000, then the
room rent of ₹2000 that you have to pay is
yours. The entire calculation is done by the
insurance company and not only the room
rent but all the expenses related to it
because as the room rent
increases, your treatment cost will
also increase. The pricing in the hospital is in
a way linked to the room rent, which
means the cost of treatment can be debited from there.
If you are taking a different room, then
your date will be different. If you have
taken a higher category room, then your entire
treatment cost will be pro-rated accordingly. So,
for doing such calculations, they
need all the bills and whatever is the doctor's
prescription plus whatever is his
diagnosis, you have to submit that to them.
Similar formalities are
applicable to all the insurance policies of the world, critical or any other type. It
depends on what type of policy it is.
Many policies are only
fixed.  There are benefit plans but for
example, if you have taken a dengue policy
which only says that if you are
diagnosed with dengue, you will
get ₹50,000 later, then there is
no need for bills etc. in that policy because there it is
only to be insured whether you have dengue or
not and for that, they ask you to
submit the documentation
but there is no need for complete detailing
because in that policy, definitely it
depends on the policy type in fixed benefit plans but in
most of the health insurance related policies, at least the
hospital bills and you know discharge etc., it becomes
mandatory
that now all these things are sometimes
written in the policy document also, sometimes they are
always written, so in such a situation,
when you sign the policy document,
when you come into the contract
with any insurance company, there are some
points which people might read, they may
forget everything else but these
points should not be forgotten, they should cross check and
verify them.  Which will be the
life insurance contract and
health insurance contract?
Yes, when we talk about contracts,
we definitely know that the
legal terms in the contract are
very difficult to read, and you know, that
date is 20-30 pages of documents, so it is
very difficult for a common man to understand them.
So our suggestion is
that whatever the insurance company is
writing about you specifically, whether it is writing in the pen of your post,
that your post was this or your
proposal form, if you read it, I
think it is very important because that is
your specific information. The rest of the
contract is a legal
contract in a way. If the insurance company
enforces that contract for everyone,
then definitely that contract will be a
fair contract. It will not happen
that it will be an unfair contract
because these contract terms and
police terms and conditions are
observed very well by the IRDP,
plus
it can also be challenged in an Indian Court of Justice. So,
generally
I would say that you should still ignore the terms and conditions, if you do
not have time or you are not able to understand it, then
read your proposal form carefully because whatever reason may arise for rejection of your claim, it
arises from there only.
I think we should end the discussion here.
Thank you very much for taking out your time
and for sharing
your information on this entire issue with the audience in such detail. So with this
we stop for a small break.